UNITED STATES GOVERNMENT Memorandum

TO: CB/ Scientist-Astronauts                          DATE: August 6, 1970.

FROM : cB/ Phil Chapman

SUBJECT: Icebergs Ahead.

It is surely clear by now that the titanic manned space program is not
as unsinkable-as it may have seemed a year ago. We have very few friends 
left, in the scientific community, in Congress, or amongst the general 
public. The budget withers, interest sags, the "middle option" for the 
'70s program seems more and more an illusory pipe-dream, and there is 
little sign of any effective action, inside NASA or out, to reverse the 
trend. The latest blow was von Braun's statement last Monday, at the
NAS meeting at Wood's Hole, that OSSA's $400 million budget proposal for 
Skylab B experiments has shot that vehicle out of the sky. If you will 
forgive the metaphor melange, I think it is high time to consider whether 
there is anything we can do as a group to shore up a bulkhead or two, or 
whether we should be prepared merely to come to attention on deck as the 
ship founders beneath us.

I, for one, have a dumb faith that man is in space to stay, and perhaps
some dramatic development will save the program -- for example, the Russians 
will surely overcome their engineering problems with their big booster and 
the Komarov malfunction, and then may shatter effectively the complacent 
feeling that we are safely ahead. But we can't depend on this sort of thing, 
and anyway we are confronting very serious damage in the interim. In ally \ 
case, our generation has the chance to lay the foundation for getting mankind 
out of the cis-lunar nursery and I don't think we should allow that historic 
privilege to be deferred to some later generation without a fight.

Many of NASA's present problems are NASA's own fault. It is of course a 
difficult time, when science and technology are depicted as destroyers of 
the environment and/or instruments of war and the nation's attention is 
engrossed in urgent problems such as VietNam and pollution and the ghettoeS. 
All that means is we must perform better and fight harder instead of meekly 
going under, crying excuses.

I would indict NASA on at least the following counts:

1) Failure to spread understanding of the importance of the program. We
have relied on spectaculars and the space race, both of which are ineffective 
now -- everything is anticlimax after Apollo 11, and the Russians are 
(seemingly) out of the running. What we are doing will be remembered when 
VietNam and even the whole communist-capitalist struggle are as dusty as
the Peloponnesian Wars, but there is little public awareness of what a 
remarkable thing it is to be living now.


2) Failure to develop a coherent and imaginative plan for what we are 
trying to do in space in the '70s. Planning for new generations of vehicles 
is generally fairly well done, but there is no strong central authority 
accepting responsibility for what we will do once in orbit. The nation 
will clearly no longer accept getting into space as an end in itself and 
there will be no program unless we exhibit a total commitment to truly 
significant and cost-effective work in space in science and applications.
We should demand the most stringent standards of excellence in the conception 
of experiments, but we are swamped in mediocrity. In view of the investment 
required, some at least of the P.I.s should have a chance for the Nobel
as a result of the experiments we do for them, but most of the work is of 
a quality which, on an objective basis, without regard for the mystique of 
having been done in space, would hardly qualify for publication in a high
school magazine. If we cannot develop a clear and defensible rationale for 
the experimental program, we should quit wasting public money on it. The 
problem is apparent even in mainline, where NASA is very vulnerable because 
each mission, which now can have no other justification than science, costs 
over half the annual NSF budget -- but there is virtually no attempt to 
discuss openly and candidly why the incremental value of each new set of
lunar rocks or each new ALSEP on the surface justifies this expenditure.
Much worse is Skylab, where, with a few notable exceptions, the experiments
are miserable trivia, whether they be concerned with science, technology or
applications. I cringe at the thought of trying to defend Skylab before
a technical audience, once the paltry inanities of the experimental program
are embarrassingly clear. If NASA is in trouble now, just wait until the
enemies of the program learn what we are spending on such great breakthroughs
as potato circadian rhythm and the gravity substitute electric chair. The 
only possible way-we can get away with Skylab A is by claiming that it is 
principally a necessary demonstration of human endurance in free fall --
and that rug is likely to be jerked out from under us by a Russian long-term 
flight before Skylab flies. Unless Skylab B goes with a significant suite 
of experiments, there will be nothing after about the end of 1973 until the 
advent of the shuttle -- and that won't be until the '80s unless we do a 
much better job of demonstrating a value for man in space than we have so
far, or will in Skylab. What I have seen of the experiment definition for 
the space station and space base exhibits the same sorry signs of gestation 
by committee, which is responsible for most of the congenital defects of 
*Skylab, instead of the strength and creativity which is mandatory to justify 
those programs and the shuttle.


3) Failure to adapt managerial policies which were effective during the 
massive, time-critical phase of Apollo, when cost-effectiveness was 
subordinate to getting the job done, to the realities of the operational 
and utilitarian program of this decade. Over-design of systems (for a 
trivial example, have a look at the milled aluminum doors of the Skylab 
lockers in Dick Truly's office), failure to streamline documentation, 
maintenance of bureaucratic structures which are no longer relevant, 
acceptance of incredible costs for fixing minor Bins and a lack of a hard- 
nosed, cost-conscious central direction are just inexcusable in the context 
of the program with which we are now dealing. In system after system for 
Skylab, the engineering and even the fundamental concepts are simply
incompetent, and failure to discard the obsolete management practices which 
have allowed this is nothing short of dereliction of responsibility to the 
space program and the nation.

It is, of course, easy to be critical in this crisis for NASA. The only 
meaningful question, however, is what we can do, as individuals or as a 
group, to move towards correcting the situation. I would like to suggest 
the following:

i) We should speak out boldly and loudly and often in in-house circles 
about the fundamental problems listed above, especially #2, where we 
should have a special competence. If this treads on some toes, or offends
our hierarchical superiors, or steps outside our assigned responsibilities, 
that is preferable to sitting back passively while the program collapses.

ii) We should make a vigorous effort to formulate a clear understanding 
amongst ourselves as to why man has a useful role in space, especially 
for scientific purposes, and then try harder to influence our scientific 
peers, by attending meetings, giving papers, and writing for publication. 
When we have access to the Press, we should abandon the platitudes of the 
party line and speak out strongly on the fundamental purposes of the program 
and its relationship to other social goals. We should not be afraid of 
constructively criticizing NASA where that seems appropriate.

iii) If Skylab B fails to fly, and no alternative project is defined and
ft approved for the mid-Seventies, the manned spaceflight program is very likely 
to lose all momentum and the nation will be faced with a serious and costly 
problem of re-building the organization when external conditions eventually 
demand that we get back into space. If lack of an economical and effective 
experimental program is killing Skylab B, I suggest that we tackle this 
problem by ourselves, as an independent project. I would like to ask each
of you to come up with a list of at least five significant experiments in 
your discipline, either from your own_ingenuity or as a result of talking 
to your colleagues in NASA or elsewhere. If we truly believe that there 
is anything meaningful for us to do as scientists in space, we should be 
able to back up the conviction with some concrete examples. After a 
candid and critical bull session to cull out the trivial and insignificant 
or overly ambitious from the resulting list of (hopefully) 75 to 100
experiments, we can enlist the aid of experts as needed to form preliminary 
estimates of weight and power and space and cost requirements, and finally 
come up with a document setting forth an example of a complete suite of 
important experiments for a mission in the Skylab class. I believe we
can do this because we are almost certainly the most highly-selected group 
of scientists which has ever been assembled and probably represent the 
strongest concentration of diverse scientific talent which exists in NASA, 
if not in the country. I am quite impressed with the potential capabilities 
of the scientist-astronauts, compared to other scientific groups I have 
worked with in the past, even if we have had little opportunity as yet to 
demonstrate the contribution we are capable of making to the program. I
am proud to be a member of this team. Furthermore, for the present purpose, 
we have the great advantages of interdisciplinary contacts among ourselves 
and a better understanding of what is and is not feasible in space than is 
available to scientists outside the astronaut office. The resulting 
document, if well done, could have a considerable impact not only in NASA
HQ but in the National Academy of Sciences and other scientific circles, 
demonstrating that a little dedication and imagination can in fact generate  
a significant scientific program for man in space.

If I get a favorable response from most of you to this suggestion, I shall 
ask Tom and Deke to allow us some time from our other responsibilities
to work on this, but I think we should be prepared to do it in our own 
time if necessary. I shall offer my house and a copious supply of beer 
to this project and undertake to act as file clerk and administrative 
factotum. To be effective, we need to finish the project as soon as 
possible, certainly within a couple of months.

I have tried to word this memo strongly, but I think I have understated the  
seriousness of the crisis facing manned spaceflight. I do not think we 
would be usurping the function of anybody in undertaking to generate a 
meaningful scientific program for Skylab B, because there does not seem
to be any unified group in NASA charged with this responsibility, which 
is now left largely to the chance response from the scientific community
to Flight Opportunities announcements. OS7s, and the MSFEB serve primarily 
a critical rather than a creative function -- and of course I would expect 
to submit the output of the study to these organizations if it got as far 
as being a serious proposal. Right now, the important thing seems to be
to give a powerful example of a creative program, unified and scientifically 
sound and offering a good return on the investment. I would therefore 
envisage the document as falling somewhere between the typical Blue Book
of candidate experiments and and an actual proposed program.

It is possible that, in the course of this study, we might come up with 
some experiments which were sufficiently cheap and easy to build to have
a chance still of flying on Skylab A, especially if, as seems likely, that 
project slips further, thereby offering an opportunity to alleviate the 
disaster for the credibility of man in space NASA will confront when called
upon to defend its experimental program.for those missions.

The basic message I am trying to put across here is a call to action in 
defense of the program, and I would certainly welcome any suggestions for 
other things we might do.